<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>James A. Falcone</origin><pubdate>2018</pubdate><title>Changes in imperviousness for U.S. urban areas, 1974-2012</title><geoform>Comma-separated text files</geoform><onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/P975GGZQ</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This product consists of two sets of imperviousness calculations for 3,535 urban areas and urban clusters in the conterminous United States. Imperviousness is given as the percent of the area covered by impervious surfaces, such as roads, buildings, or parking lots.  One set of calculations is for the time periods 2001, 2006, and 2011, based on the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) National Land Cover Dataset (NLCD) imperviousness data layer.  The second set of calculations is for the time periods 1974, 1982, 1992, 2002, and 2012, based on landuse-based coefficients from the USGS NAWQA Wall-to-wall Anthropogenic Landuse Trends (NWALT) product.  Urban area boundaries are based on the U.S. Census Bureau 2015 Urban Areas boundaries.  The Census Bureau polygon shapefile on which the calculations were based is also provided.</abstract><purpose>These data are intended as a way to compare changes in urban areas over time, and to compare relative differences among cities. See Supplemental Info for recommended use of the data.</purpose><supplinf>Two comma-separated text files are given here as well as the Census Bureau shapefile used as the basis for calculations. Each table contains 3,535 rows, one for each of the records in the shapefile. Urban areas boundaries are based on the 2015 1:500k Census boundaries.
The Urban Areas shapefile obtained from the Census Bureau contained 3,535 unique areas within the conterminous United States.  Of these, 481 were classified by Census as "Urban Areas" (UA, UATYP10 = "U") and 3,054 were classified as "Urban Clusters" (UC, UATYP10 = "C").  For the purpose of this dataset these are treated identically, and in this document all referred to as "urban areas". See https://www.census.gov/geo/reference/ua/urban-rural-2010.html for more information on the differences between an Area and a Cluster. In essence, a UA is a densely settled area of at least 50,000 people, and a UC is a densely settled area of at least 2,500 people but less than 50,000. 
The tables are derived from two different sources and may differ to some degree. Imperviousness from the National Land Cover Dataset (NLCD) is derived primarily from remote sensing sources (see Xian and others, 2011 and Homer and others, 2015), while imperviousness from the NAWQA Wall-to-wall Anthropogenic Landuse Trends (NWALT, Falcone, 2015) dataset is derived from land use class-based coefficients (Falcone, 2017).  The NLCD imperviousness is likely to be more accurate with regard to absolute values, but is limited to the years 2001-2011, while NWALT-derived values span 1974-2012. If the user's period of analysis does not extend before 2001 it is recommended to use the NLCD values. The data sources are not directly comparable.  That is, users should use either the NLCD values as a time series, or the NWALT-derived values as a time series, but not mix them. 
For two urban areas, Bar Harbor and Calais, Maine, NWALT-derived imperviousness values were derived from an unpublished update to the data in Falcone, 2017.  This was due to a portion of the eastern tip of Maine being masked out in the original NWALT-derived source data.
Accuracy, particularly for the NWALT values, is likely to vary with the size of the urban area.  The urban areas measured here vary by four orders of magnitude in size: from less than 1 square kilometer (Richgrove, California) to nearly 10,000 square kilometers (New York city area).  Values are likely to be more accurate for large areas versus small areas.  In the creation of the NWALT-based product (Falcone, 2017) the results were compared for the 2002 product to the NLCD 2001 for HUC-12 watersheds nationwide.  In that comparison, there was an r2 agreement of 0.93 and 96% of HUC-12s agreed to within 1% of the imperviousness of the NLCD.  However the median size of HUC-12s is approximately 88 square kilometers, whereas the median size of the urban areas measured here is approximately 13 square kilometers.  Users are advised to be more cautious in interpreting results, particularly for the NWALT data, as the urban area decreases. 
The data here are intended as a way of comparing relative imperviousness of urban areas and changes over time, but not necessarily as the "definitive measurement" of imperviousness for each city.  The measurement for a city depends to a large degree on which boundaries are used.  The boundaries used here, U.S. Census 2015 Urban Areas, while an authoritative source, may differ from city incorporated boundaries, and also differ from boundaries for Metropolitan Statistical Areas (MSAs) (collections of complete counties around a city).  For example, the urban area for Washington DC given here ("Washington, DC-VA-MD") is an area extending to parts of (but not all of) 15 counties around the city.  A measurement for the Metropolitan Statistical Area of Washington ("Washington-Arlington-Alexandria, DC-VA-MD-WV"), would be based on MSA boundaries which include 24 complete counties, and give a different result. (See https://www.census.gov/data/tables/2016/demo/popest/total-metro-and-micro-statistical-areas.html for more information about MSAs).  That is, users should consider this as "one way" of measuring the imperviousness of the Washington, DC urban area.
All NLCD data are derived from the October 2014 harmonized versions of the NLCD 2001, 2006, 2011 (mrlc.gov).  The stated USGS preferred citations for NLCD products are: 
NLCD 2001 products: Homer and others, 2007.
NLCD 2006 products: Fry and others, 2011
NLCD 2011 products: Homer and others, 2015.
NLCD 2011 Percent Developed Imperviousness specifically: Xian and others, 2011
References:
Falcone, J.A., 2015, U.S. conterminous wall-to-wall anthropogenic land use trends (NWALT), 1974-2012. U.S. Geological Survey Data Series 948, 33 p. plus appendices 3-6 as separate files, http://dx.doi.org/10.3133/ds948.
Falcone, J.A., 2017, Coefficient-based consistent mapping of imperviousness in the conterminous U.S. at 60-m resolution for 1974, 1982, 1992, 2002, and 2012: U.S. Geological Survey data release, https://doi.org/10.5066/F72F7KMG.
Fry, J., Xian, G., Jin, S., Dewitz, J., Homer, C., Yang, L., Barnes, C., Herold, N., and Wickham, J., 2011, Completion of the 2006 National Land Cover Database for the Conterminous United States, Photogrammetric Engineering and Remote Sensing, Vol. 77(9):858-864. 
Homer, C., Dewitz, J., Fry, J., Coan, M., Hossain, N., Larson, C., Herold, N., McKerrow, A., VanDriel, J.N., and Wickham, J., 2007, Completion of the 2001 National Land Cover Database for the Conterminous United States, Photogrammetric Engineering and Remote Sensing, Vol. 73, No. 4, pp 337-341.
Homer, C.G., Dewitz, J.A., Yang, L., Jin, S., Danielson, P., Xian, G., Coulston, J., Herold, N.D., Wickham, J.D., and Megown, K., 2015, Completion of the 2011 National Land Cover Database for the conterminous United States-Representing a decade of land cover change information. Photogrammetric Engineering and Remote Sensing, v. 81, no. 5, p. 345-354. 
U.S. Census Bureau, 2016, Cartographic Boundary Shapefiles - Urban Areas, 1:500k boundaries, accessed February 17, 2016 at: https://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/cbf/cbf_ua.html.
Xian, G., Homer, C., Dewitz, J., Fry, J., Hossain, N., and Wickham, J., 2011, The change of impervious surface area between 2001 and 2006 in the conterminous United States., Photogrammetric Engineering and Remote Sensing, Vol. 77(8): 758-762.</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>19740101</begdate><enddate>20121231</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><current>observed</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-124.886</westbc><eastbc>-66.879</eastbc><northbc>49.384</northbc><southbc>24.381</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>inlandWaters</themekey><themekey>Land use</themekey><themekey>Imperviousness</themekey><themekey>NLCD</themekey><themekey>NWALT</themekey></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>United States</placekey><placekey>Conterminous US</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst><useconst>Please read use constraints for individual data layers, as applicable.</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>US Geological Survey, National Water Quality project.</cntorg><cntper>James Falcone</cntper></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing</addrtype><address>12201 Sunrise Valley Dr.</address><address>MS 413 National Center</address><city>Reston</city><state>VA</state><postal>20192</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>703-648-5008</cntvoice><cntemail>jfalcone@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><datacred>Great thanks to Laura Hayes for performing product review.</datacred><native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.3.1 (Build 4959) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>No formal accuracy tests were performed on these data, however the NLCD-based data are likely to be more accurate. NWALT-derived values should be considered estimates, but are based on consistent methods and data. See note in Supplemental Info regarding accuracy.</attraccr></attracc><logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic><complete>Data are complete</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Census Bureau</origin><pubdate>20160217</pubdate><title>Published 2015 Urban Area boundaries</title><geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (polygon)</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>online</pubplace><publish>U.S. Census Bureau</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/cbf/cbf_ua.html</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20160217</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>access date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>U.S. Census Bureau, 2016</srccitea><srccontr>2015 Urban Area boundaries, 1:500k, used in data calculations.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>MRLC Consortium</origin><pubdate>20141001</pubdate><title>NLCD 2001 Percent Developed Imperviousness (2011 Edition)</title><geoform>Raster Data Set</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>online</pubplace><publish>NLCD 2001</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://www.mrlc.gov/nlcd01_data.php</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>20010101</begdate><enddate>20011231</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>ground condition</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>NLCD 2001, Homer and others, 2007</srccitea><srccontr>NLCD 2001 dataset from which imperviousness 2001 imperviousness was derived</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>MRLC Consortium</origin><pubdate>20141001</pubdate><title>NLCD 2006 Percent Developed Imperviousness (2011 Edition)</title><geoform>Raster Data Set</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>online</pubplace><publish>NLCD 2006</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://www.mrlc.gov/nlcd06_data.php</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>20060101</begdate><enddate>20061231</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>ground condition</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>NLCD 2006, Fry and others, 2011</srccitea><srccontr>NLCD 2006 dataset from which imperviousness 2006 imperviousness was derived</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>MRLC Consortium</origin><pubdate>20141001</pubdate><title>NLCD 2011 Percent Developed Imperviousness and NLCD 2011 USFS Tree Canopy cartographic</title><geoform>Raster Data Set</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>online</pubplace><publish>NLCD 2011</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://www.mrlc.gov/nlcd11_data.php</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>20110101</begdate><enddate>20111231</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>ground condition</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>NLCD 2011, Xian and others, 2011; Homer and others, 2015</srccitea><srccontr>NLCD 2011 datasets from which imperviousness 2011 was derived</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin><pubdate>20170301</pubdate><title>Coefficient-based consistent mapping of imperviousness in the conterminous U.S. at 60-m resolution for 1974, 1982, 1992, 2002, and 2012</title><geoform>Raster Data Set</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>online</pubplace><publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo><onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/F72F7KMG</onlink></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>Digital and/or Hardcopy Resources</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>19740101</begdate><enddate>20121231</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>ground condition</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>NAWQA Wall-to-wall Anthropogenic Landuse Trends (NWALT) 1974-2012</srccitea><srccontr>NWALT-derived dataset from which imperviousness 1974-2012 were derived</srccontr></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>(1) Source data of urban areas was downloaded from the U.S. Census Bureau on February 17, 2015 from https://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/cbf/cbf_ua.html</procdesc><procdate>20160217</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>(2) Source data from the NLCD were downloaded (https://www.mrlc.gov/) and converted to grid format in March 2015. The source data for the NLCD are the October 2014 normalized version of data, where all years have been adjusted to agree with one another.</procdesc><procdate>20160315</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>(3) Source data of imperviousness grids derived from NWALT were based on Falcone (2017).</procdesc><procdate>20170103</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>(4) The Census shapefile was subsetted to only those urban areas in the continental U.S. (CONUS). A unique id field was added for ease of internal processing.  The area of each polygon was calculated from the polygon geometry.</procdesc><procdate>20180104</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>(5) The shapefile was converted to a national 100-meter grid. Mean imperviousness was then calculated from that using the zonalmean() command in ArcGIS Grid.</procdesc><procdate>20180104</procdate></procstep></lineage></dataqual><eainfo><detailed Name="imperv_nlcd2001-2011.txt, imperv_nwalt1974-2012.txt, shapefile-Census-UAs-2015-CONUS.zip"><enttyp><enttypl>Attribute Table for imperviousness data</enttypl><enttypd>Data consist of two comma-separated text files and a zip file which contains the Urban Area boundaries in polygon shapefile format. The two tables are: imperv_nlcd2001-2011.txt, imperv_nwalt1974-2012.txt.</enttypd><enttypds>Surface Water Trends project, USGS National Water Quality Program</enttypds></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>GEOID10</attrlabl><attrdef>Geographic identifier associated with the urban area, provided by Census Bureau</attrdef><attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Five digit unique identifier from Census</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>NAME10</attrlabl><attrdef>Urban area name, provided by Census Bureau</attrdef><attrdefs>U.S. Census Bureau</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Five digit unique identifier from Census</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>uniqid</attrlabl><attrdef>Unique id assigned for internal processing</attrdef><attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Unique id assigned for internal processing only</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>area_km2</attrlabl><attrdef>Area in square kilometers of urban area polygon</attrdef><attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0.7</rdommin><rdommax>9380.9</rdommax><attrunit>Square kilometers</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>imperv_nlcdXXXX</attrlabl><attrdef>Percent imperviousness from NLCD data, for 2001, 2006, and 2011 (year represented by XXXX)</attrdef><attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0.14</rdommin><rdommax>57.22</rdommax><attrunit>Percent</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>imperv_nwaltXXXX</attrlabl><attrdef>Percent imperviousness from NWALT-derived data, for 1974, 1982, 1992, 2002, 2012 (year represented by XXXX)</attrdef><attrdefs>U.S. Geological Survey</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0.41</rdommin><rdommax>46.51</rdommax><attrunit>Percent</attrunit></rdom></attrdomv></attr></detailed></eainfo><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>US Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing</addrtype><address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address><city>Denver</city><state>CO</state><postal>80225</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>1-888-275-8747 (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice><cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>Although this data set has been used by the U.S. Geological
Survey, U.S. Department of the Interior, no warranty expressed or
implied is made by the U.S. Geological Survey as to the accuracy
of the data and related materials. The act of distribution shall not 
constitute any such warranty, and no responsibility is assumed by 
the U.S. Geological Survey in the use of this data, software, or 
related materials.
Any use of trade, product, or firm names is for descriptive 
purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. 
Government.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Tabular Digital Data Set</formname></digtinfo><digtopt><onlinopt><computer><networka><networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/P975GGZQ</networkr></networka></computer></onlinopt></digtopt></digform><fees>None. This dataset is provided by USGS as a public service.</fees></stdorder></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20180409</metd><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>James Falcone</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Ask USGS -- Water Webserver Team</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing</addrtype><address>12201 Sunrise Valley Dr., MS 413</address><city>Reston</city><state>VA</state><postal>20192</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>1-888-275-8747 (1-888-ASK-USGS)</cntvoice><cntemail>https://answers.usgs.gov/</cntemail></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv></metainfo></metadata>